Guide to the Ellsworth Eliot Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
Ellsworth Eliot Collection
1768-1908
RG 210
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(5 boxes)
The collection consists primarily of published books, pamphlets and articles collected by Ellsworth Eliot Sr. The annotated collected documents reflect Eliot's varied research interests, particularly the life and work of his ancestor, John Eliot, "Apostle to the Indians."
Eliot, Ellsworth, 1827-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Eliot D. Hawkins, Evelyn B. Patterson, and Alice Van Tuyl, 2009
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Ellsworth Eliot, Sr., was born in North Guilford, CT on September 15, 1827. Ellsworth's great-grandfather, Abigall Eliot, was the son of Joseph Eliot, who was son of John Eliot, "The Apostle to the Indians." Ellsworth Eliot graduated from Yale College in 1849, and attended first Yale Medical School and then the College of Physicians and Surgeons in New York City, receiving his medical degree in 1852. Ellsworth Eliot's chief hobby was collecting documentation related to the Eliot family genealogy. Fruits of that labor are evident in this collection of Eliot-related materials. Ellsworth Eliot retired from active medical practice in 1898 and died on December9, 1912. For more detailed biographical information, see Box 1, Folder 1.
Ellsworth Eliot's ancestor John Eliot is credited with being one of the editors of the Bay Psalm Book, which was the first book published in the British North American colonies. He was a missionary to native Americans in Massachusetts and translated the Bible into their native language (published 1663). In 1666, he published a "The Indian Grammar Begun." Eliot was known for attempting to preserve the culture of the Native Americans by putting them in planned towns where they could continue by their own rule as a Christian society. At one point in time, there were fourteen of these towns of so-called "Praying Indians", the best documented being at Natick, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents
These materials collected by Ellsworth Eliot, Sr. provide a valuable consolidated resource of publications related to John Eliot and the Eliot family. A detailed inventory of the collection, with transcriptions of annotations and notes by Ellsworth Eliot, is available in Box 1, Folder 1. The majority of the items in the collection are published works. The materials reflect Ellsworth Eliot Sr.'s varied research interests, particularly the life and work of his ancestor, John Eliot, "Apostle to the Indians", as well as church history and family history in the Connecticut shoreline towns of Clinton, Guilford, Madison, and North Branford, and Massachusett towns in the Boston vicinity. Nearly all of the publications contain personal notes or additional material such as newspaper clippings that were added by Ellsworth Eliot. These notes typically list references to John Eliot, "Apostle to the Indians," or other descendants of John Eliot that appear in the publication. Some notes explain a connection between the publication's subject matter and the Eliot family.
Arrangement
I. John Eliot / Eliot Family, 1833-1901
II. Connecticut History / Eliot Family, 1850-1902
III. Massachusetts History / Eliot Family, 1768-1908
Bible. Massachuset. Eliot; Indians of North America -- Missions; Indians of North America -- New England; Eliot, John, 1604-1690
- John Eliot / Eliot Family, 1833-1901; Series I
  - Inventory of the collection and biographical material about Ellsworth Eliot, Sr. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1. Eliot Memorial. Sketches Historical and Biographical of the Eliot Church and Society Boston. By A.C. Thompson. Boston. The Pilgrim Press. Chicago., 1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 2. Eliot Anniversary, 1646-1896. City of Newton, Memorial Exercises, November 11, 1896. Newton: Published by Order of the City of the City Council. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 3. Memorial Sermons in Recognition of the Two Hundred and Fiftieth Anniversary of the Founding of the First Religious Society in Roxbury. By the Minister, Rev. John Graham Brooks. Boston: Published for the Society by George H. Ellis., 1882 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 4. Mémoire Sur Le Système Grammatical Des Langues De Quelques Nations Indiennes De L'Amèrique Du Nord; Ouvrage Qui, A La Séance Publique Annuelle De L'Institut Royal de France, Le 2 Mai 1835, a remporté le prix fondé par M. le comte de Volney; Par M. P.-T. Du Ponceau, LL.D, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 5. Missionary Labors of the Apostle Eliot. A Discourse Delivered October 25, 1896, Two Hundred and Fifty Years From the Time Those Labors Were Begun. By Rev. Daniel L. Furber, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 6. Remarks on the Rev. Robert Court, D.D., and John Eliot's Work at Wamesit, By Charles Cowley, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 7. The Good Indian Missionary. Written for the American Sunday-School Union, and Revised by the Committee of Publication. Philadelphia: American Sunday School Union. No. 146 Chestnut Street., 1833 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 8. Bibliographic Notes on Eliot's Indian Bible and On His Other Translations and Works in the Indian Language of Massachusetts. Extract from a "Bibliography of the Algonquian Languages" Washington. Government Printing Office., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 9. John Eliot's First Indian Interpreter. Cockenoe-De-Long Island and The Story of his Career from the Early Records. By William Wallace Tooker. New York. Francis P. Harper., 1896 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 10. Lives of the Fathers of New England. Vol. III. The Life of John Eliot: With An Account of the Early Missionary Efforts Among the Indians of New England. By Nehemiah Adams, Pastor of Essex Street Church, Boston, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 11. The Life of the Renowned John Eliot. By Cotton Mather. 1691, American Antiquarian Society; "dup." By Sam Well, Worcester, 1840 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 12. The Life of the Rev. John Eliot, The Apostle to the Indians. Christian Biography. Religious Tract Society (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 13. Narré Du Voyage Faict Pour La Mission Des Abnaquiois et des Connaissances tiréz de la Nouvelle Angleterre et des dispositions des Magistrats de cette Republique pour le fecours contre les Iroquois, ès années 1650 & 1651. Par Le R. Père Gabriel Dreuilletee de las Compagnie de Jesus., 1855 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 14. Indian Bible Catechism / A single leaf at the end of Eliot's Indian Bible, -- in both the first and second editions, -- contains a Catechism for the Indians, or more exactly, some rules and directions for leading a religious life, in the form of answers to the two questions, "How can I walk with God all day long? And "What should a Christian do to keep the Sabbath day perfectly holy?"…Hartford, Conn., 1865 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 15. Law and Life, from John Eliot, the Apostle to the Indian Nations of New England. By Robert Boodey Caverly, of the Massachusetts, U.S., Bar. Boston, Mass.: Moses H. Sargent & Sons. 1880. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - 16. John Eliot, The Puritan Missionary to the Indians. By Ezra Hoyt Byington, D.D. Newton, Massachusetts. [Reprinted from Vol. VIII., American Society of Church History.] The Knickerbocker Press, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - 17. John Eliot. Oration by William Sidney Elliott, Jr., (A Lineal Descendant). Delivered at the Second Meeting of the Descendants of John Eliot, "Apostle to the Indian," held at South Natick, Massachusetts, July Third, Nineteen Hundred and One, upon the Two Hundred and Fiftieth Anniversary of the Founding there by him, of the Village of "Praying Indians.", 1901 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - 18. Strength of Weakness: or a Glorious Manifestation of the Further Progress of the Gospel Among the Indians in New England. By Henry Witfield. New York: Reprinted for Joseph Abin. Sabin's Reprints, Quarto Series. No. V., 1865 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - 19. Selections relating to John Eliot, "Apostle to the Indians," and his descendants. Collected by Ellsworth Eliot. Bound in 1891. New York, N.Y. Vol. I. (61 items) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - 20. Selections relating to John Eliot, "Apostle to the Indians," and his descendants. Collected by Ellsworth Eliot. Bound in 1891. New York, N.Y. Vol. II. (28 items) (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - 21. Selections relating to John Eliot, "Apostle to the Indians," and his descendants." Collected by Ellsworth Eliot. Bound in 1892. New York, N.Y. Vol. III. (17 items) (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - 22. Eliot Selections. Pamphlets, bound together. Vol. IV (6 items) (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - 23. Selections relating to John Eliot, "Apostle to the Indians," and his descendants. Collected by Ellsworth Eliot. Bound in 1893. (9 items) (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - 24. Notebook. Articles, Paragraphs, etc. Relating to John Eliot, "Apostle to the Indians," or to some member of his family, and his descendants. Derived from various sources. Began. July 1889 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - 25. Pamphlets and Selections from Magazines and Books relating to the Society for promoting and propagating the Gospel in New England Collected by Ellsworth Eliot. Bound in 1890. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - 26. Mr. Eliot's Sermon on Exodus 1.21 (typescript transcription of 1739 sermon by Jared Eliot) (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Connecticut History / Eliot Family, 1850-1902; Series II
  - 1. First Congregational Church. Madison, Connecticut. Historical Discourse. 170th Anniversary., 1877 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - 2. Clinton, Connecticut. Congregational Church. 200th Anniversary, 1867 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - 4. The Early History of the Congregational Church and Society, of North Branford. Delivered in the Congregational Church, Jan. 6 1850. By George I. Wood. Published by Request. New Haven: Printed by J.H. Benham, Orange Street. 1850., 1902, 1850 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - 5. The Ministers of the Revolution. The Report of the Committee Appointed by the General Association of Connecticut. By Wm. Chauncey Fowler, LL.D. Hartford: Press of the Case, Lockwood & Brainard Company., 1877 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - 7. Manual of the First Congregational Church, Guilford, Conn., January 1, 1875. New Haven: Printed by Tuttle, Morehouse & Taylor., 1895, 1875 (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Massachusetts History / Eliot Family, 1768-1908; Series III
  - 1. Dedication of the First Unitarian Church. South Natick, Massachusetts. Addresses delivered by Rev. J.P. Sheafe. Rev. Horatio Alger. Semi-Centennial Celebration. November 20, 1878. Natick, Massachusetts. Ryder & Morse, Printers. Citizens Office, 1879 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - 2. Trinity Church. Boston. Consecration Services. February 9, 1877, with the Consecration Sermon, by Rev. A.H. Vinton, D.D. an Historical Sermon, by Rev. Phillips Brooks, and a Description of the church Edifice by H.H. Richardson, Architect. Boston: Printed by Order of the Vestry. (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - 3. Bound Pamphlets, "Roxbury and Natick Pamphlets (16 items), 1768-1908 (Box 5, Folder 35)